<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article xml:lang="en-US">
  <meta>
    <author email="info@xopus.com">multiple authors</author>
    <date>2009-07-01</date>
    <categories>
      <category>Art</category>
      <category>Travel</category>
      <category>Sports</category>
    </categories>
  </meta>
  <h>The Netherlands</h>
  <section>
    <h>Introduction</h>
    <figure align="right">
      <img src="content/windmill-leiden.jpg" width="240" border-type="soft" />
      <legend>Windmill in Leiden</legend>
    </figure>
    <p>
      The <strong>Netherlands</strong> is a flatter than flat country most
      commonly associated with tulips, windmills, clogs and cheese. While such
      clichéd images of the Netherlands still hold true, Holland offers
      travellers much more than the stereotypical national quirks. It&#x2019;s
      a small, vibrant nation that can be traversed in a few hours - but it
      begs a longer stay than that. 
    </p>
    <p>
      Amsterdam is the notorious capital, known for everything from its liberal
      approach to drugs and prostitution, to its network of canals,
      world-famous museums and historical architecture.
    </p>

    <quote>
      <body>
        Those Dutchmen had hardly any imagination or fantasy, but their good
        taste and their scientific knowledge of composition were enormous.
      </body> 
      <source>
        <a href="http://strangewondrous.net/search?query=firstName:Vincent+AND+lastName:Gogh">Vincent van Gogh</a>
      </source>
    </quote>
  </section>
  <section>
    <h>Brief History</h>
    <section>
      <h>Early History</h>
      <p>The Low Countries (current-day Netherlands, Belgium and Luxembourg) had been inhabited by Germanic tribes since 600 BC when the Romans conquered it around 10 BC. The cities of Utrecht, Nijmegen and Maastricht<note view="below-article">
        <a href="http://nl.wikipedia.org/wiki/Traiectum">Traiectum</a>, <a href="http://nl.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ulpia_Noviomagus_Batavorum">Batavorum</a>, and <a href="http://nl.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mosa_Trajectum">Mosa Trajectum</a> respectively in Latin.
      </note> were the Netherlands&#x2019; first major cities, built during the Roman occupation. As the Low Countries experienced more Germanic immigration, Roman culture was supplanted by three main people groups: the Frisians, the Saxons and the Franks.</p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <h>The Middle Ages</h>
      <p>Enterprising farmers from Utrecht and Flanders moved to the largely uninhabited western region of the Netherlands around 1000 AD and began to cultivate the land, sparking a rapid movement into the area. It was during this period that this area first became known as &#x201c;Holland&#x201d;, which refers to the woodlands around present-day Leiden.</p>
      <p>The Low Countries passed in and out of foreign hands during the Middle
      Ages, going through a Burgundian period and a spell under the Austrian
      Habsburgs, before Phillip II of Spain took control in the middle of the
      16<sup>th</sup> century. His suppressive regime sparked a revolt in
      1568, inspiring the proclamation of one of Europe&#x2019;s first
      republics, preceded only by Venice. Led by William of Orange, this revolt
      was basically a Catholic versus Protestant clash. It marked the beginning
      of the 80 year war, which eventually ended in 1648 with the Treaty/Peace
      of Münster, where Dutch independence was recognized by Spain.</p> <p>The
      Netherlands had become an important seafaring country during the Middle
      Ages. Amsterdam grew in importance as a trading port. After independence,
      the new republic became one of the leading countries on the world seas
      with a colonial presence in Asia (especially Indonesia and Japan). The
      Netherlands and Belgium separated and became independent countries in
      1830. Both are constitutional monarchies, meaning that the executive
      branch is headed by the monarch (even though in modern days, the role of
      the Dutch queen and Belgian king in the legislative process is confined
      to certain ceremonial duties).</p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <h>Golden Age, decline and French rule</h>
      <p>(The glory days of the Netherlands, left to be added as an exercise)</p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <h>20<sup>th</sup> Century</h>
      <p>The Netherlands was neutral during the 1st World War, but the
      2<sup>nd</sup> World War was a disaster. Germany invaded the country in
      May 1940 and occupied it for 5 years. The second half of the 20<sup>th</sup> century
      saw the Netherlands play an active role in international organizations
      such as NATO and the EEC (which later became the European Union). By
      1963, it had granted independence to most of its overseas
      territories.</p> 
      <p>In the decade after the Second World War, immigrants
      from countries like Turkey and Morocco came to the Netherlands. They now
      form an important sector of the country&#x2019;s multicultural society.
      Recent Dutch history has been marked by two notorious killings, both of
      which had a political and religious aspect: the murder of politician Pim
      Fortuyn and film director Theo van Gogh. That said, national confidence
      in the political and economic situation are better than previously.</p>
      <p>In a consultative referendum held in 2005, the majority of Dutch voters rejected a proposal for a constitutional European treaty, thereby seriously marginalizing the role of the Netherlands in determining the course of the European Union of which it once was one of the founders. The current government is divided as to the question whether the newly agreed treaty should again be subjected to a referendum.</p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <h>Monarchy of the Netherlands</h>
      <p>The Netherlands has been an independent monarchy since 16 March 1815, and has been governed by members of the House of Orange-Nassau since.</p>
      <figure align="center">
        <orgchart border-type="soft">
          <person name="Wilhelmina" division="House of Orange-Nassau">
            <person name="Juliana">
              <person name="Beatrix">
                <person name="Willem-Alexander">
                  <person name="Amalia"/>
                  <person name="Ariane"/>
                  <person name="Alexia"/>
                </person>
                <person name="Constantijn"/>
                <person name="Friso"/>
              </person>
            </person>
          </person>
        </orgchart>
      </figure>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <h>Geography</h>
    <p>The Netherlands&#x2019; surface, as its name indicates (&#x201c;nether&#x201d; means
    low), is mostly below sea level and protected by dikes. Where it rises
    above sea level, the land is still rather flat and generally only rises
    several meters above sea level. Only a very small portion of this already
    small country is hilly. This is in the southeast, in the province of
    Limburg, where the Vaalserberg on the border with Belgium and Germany
    (&#x201c;berg&#x201d; means mountain) is the Netherlands&#x2019; highest point at about 320
    meters above sea level. Much of the land in the Netherlands has been
    reclaimed from the sea - like the entirety of Flevoland, the 12<sup>th</sup> province.
    Flevoland is now in the IJsselmeer (&#x201c;meer&#x201d; means lake), but used to be
    submerged in the Zuiderzee (&#x201c;zee&#x201d; sea). </p> 
    <p>Apart from the sea, there
    are also lots of rivers in the country, with the Maas, Waal and Rhine the
    most important ones, mostly flowing from east to west. These rivers have
    their sources in France or in the mountains of Switzerland, as is the case
    for the Rhine. This means that when there has been lots of snow or rain in
    these parts, parts of the Netherlands can be flooded.</p>
    <p>The Netherlands is bordered by Belgium to the south and Germany to the east. The North Sea lies to the north and west, home to the Wadden Islands, a unique ecosystem that is part of the provinces of North Holland (Noord-Holland), Friesland and Groningen. At low tide it is possible to walk from the mainland to the islands with a guide.</p>
  </section>
  <section view="accordion">
    <h>Regions</h>
    <p>The provinces of the Netherlands are:</p>
    <p>
      You can see why the Netherlands is nicknamed <em>Holland</em> by the names of both North Holland and South Holland, where the cities of Amsterdam, Rotterdam and The Hague are based.
    </p>
    <p>In addition to the provinces, another important region is Randstad, which is roughly the triangle between Amsterdam, Utrecht and Rotterdam. With half of the Dutch population living in this area, it is of considerable economic and cultural significance.</p>
    <section>
      <h>Groningen</h>
      <p>Located in the north with the capital with the same name. It also includes several of the Wadden Islands, like Rottumeroog.</p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <h>Friesland</h>
      <p>West of Groningen, this province has its own language (Friesian or Frysk) but Dutch is understood as well. Several Wadden Islands belong to Friesland, like Terschelling and Ameland.</p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <h>Drenthe</h>
      <p>South of Groningen this province is mostly famous because of its hunebedden, or dolmen. More detailed information about these dolmen can be found on the Dolmen in the Netherlands website.</p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <h>Flevoland</h>
      <p>This is the youngest province of the country and it is totally reclaimed from the sea.</p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <h>Overijssel</h>
      <p>South of Friesland and Drenthe, this province is less known but has some nice quiet nature to enjoy and a few old hanze cities as well, like the capital Zwolle and Kampen.</p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <h>Gelderland</h>
      <p>Here you can find one of the major nature reserves in the Netherlands, called the Veluwe. Als the oldest Dutch city, Nijmegen and Arnhem are located in this province.</p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <h>Utrecht</h>
      <p>This province is in the centre of the country, with the city of Utrecht as its capital.</p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <h>North Holland</h>
      <p>In the northwest of the country, Amsterdam is located here but the capital is Haarlem.</p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <h>South Holland</h>
      <p>Although the north of this province is part of the green hart of the Netherlands, the south is mostly urban, with The Hague and Rotterdam being the biggest cities.</p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <h>Zeeland</h>
      <p>In the southwest, this province is less densely populated and has always been struggling with the sea. You can experience this struggle at the Delta Works.</p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <h>North Brabant</h>
      <p>Being one of the biggest provinces and having one of the largest populations, this province has much to offer, both for nature and culture lovers. Cities to enjoy are Breda and &#x2019;s&#160;Hertogenbosch and several nature parks like the Biesbosch are a nice way of getting away from the Dutch crowds.</p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <h>Limburg</h>
      <p>In the southeast, Maastricht is located here and the south is the only part of the country which is not totally flat.</p>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section view="tabs">
    <h>Cities</h>
      <section>
        <h>Amsterdam</h>
        <p>The vibrant capital of the Netherlands, is relatively small compared to other cities in Europe but has much to offer for the traveller, with a wide range of museums and beautifully restored old buildings along its canals.</p>
      </section>
      <section>
        <h>The Hague</h>
        <p>Located in the southwest of the country, The Hague is the political heart of the Netherlands. It also plays an important role in international law, as the International Court of Justice is located here along with another 150 international legal organizations.</p>
      </section>
      <section>
        <h>Utrecht</h>
        <p>Centrally located in the country, Utrecht is a city of some 300,000 inhabitants with a great atmosphere. Just like its bigger counterpart, Amsterdam, it enjoys a system of canals with old Dutch buildings on both sides. As it is just half an hour from Amsterdam by train, you can easily enjoy 1 or 2 days in this city and watch the famous Dom tower yourself.</p>
      </section>
      <section>
        <h>Rotterdam</h>
        <p>Almost totally destroyed in the Second World War, this second biggest city in the country is quite different to cities like Amsterdam, Utrecht or the Hague which still have a historical heart. But still, with its many museums, Erasmus bridge and large shopping district, the city deserves a visit when you have some spare time. Rotterdam also has one of the biggest ports in the world and a visit to the massive Maasvlakte by car could be one of your highlights as well if such things interest you.</p>
      </section>
      <section view="list">
        <h>Other Cities</h>
        <section>
          <h>Maastricht </h>
          <p>In the country&#x2019;s southeast, just a stone throw away of Belgium, is one of the most popular cities in the Netherlands for Dutch, Belgian and German visitors, but less so for other travellers. A pity, because it is one of those cities where enjoying good food and drinks is one of the highlights, all in again a beautifully historic heart along the shores of the Maas river.</p>
        </section>
        <section>
          <h>Groningen</h>
          <p>The biggest city in the north, Groningen is a very cosy student city with the Martini Tower as its most important building. Like many other cities outside the west of the country, few foreign visitors come here, despite the fact that it is only a couple of hours by train from Amsterdam or Utrecht. Another highlight of the city is the Groningen Museum.</p>
        </section>
        <section>
          <h>Eindhoven</h>
          <p>Being the fifth biggest city in the country, it actually has less to offer for the tourist than other major cities. One thing to enjoy though is the many pubs and great nightlife, partly because of the fact that it is a real student city, with a technical university among others. The Dutch soccer champion, PSV, has its home base here and you might be able to squeeze in a soccer game.</p>
        </section>
        <section>
          <h>Zwolle</h>
          <p>As the 19<sup>th</sup> of the twenty largest cities in the Netherlands, one would easily overlook Zwolle. Which would be a shame, as this quiet provincial capital has much to offer if you want to get away from bustling Randstad for a few days. Conveniently located 90 minutes by train from Amsterdam, Zwolle features a medieval city centre, some museums and several good bars and restaurants. The markets on Friday and Saturday offer a unique outlook on quickly disappearing Dutch folklore, when people from the villages in the Bible belt surrounding Zwolle come to town for their weekly shopping. Also, the city is a good base for cycling trips, as it is located on the divide between various geographical and cultural regions.</p>
        </section>
      </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <h>Sights and Activities</h>
    <section>
      <h>Delta Works</h>
      <p>One of the most striking things in the history of Zeeland occurred in early February 1953, when, after severe northwestern storms, coastal areas were flooded and around 1800 people got killed. Nowadays, the huge Deltaworks, which prevents the sea from rising too much when storms occur, is the most important tourist attraction in Zeeland. The Neeltje Jans Expo displays history of the flooding and explains how the Deltaworks work.</p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <h>Waddling</h>
      <p>Waddling is the act of walking on the bottom of the sea at low tide and can be done in the north of the Holland, mainly in the provinces of Friesland and Groningen. Routes will last for approximately 3-4 hours. The Wadden Islands do not only exist in the Netherlands, but also are found in Germany and Denmark. Apart from this activity, the Wadden Islands are a great place to explore one of the only true bigger natural areas of the country.</p>
      <figure align="left">
        <video src="http://www.youtube.com/v/70B6GdrXGFI" width="200" border-type="soft" />
        <legend>Waddlers in action</legend>
      </figure>
    </section>
    <section>
      <h>National Parks</h>
      <p>Despite the fact that the Netherlands is very small, it boasts about 20 national parks. In these national parks, which are almost all in the less densely populated areas of the north, east and southwest, you can cycle, walk and watch birds and other animals.</p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <h>Historic cities</h>
      <p>The Netherlands have an impressive number of historical cities, both big and small. Amsterdam and Utrecht are the most impressive bigger ones, with beautiful canals, old restored trading houses and several museums to be admired as well. But there are also several smaller ones, like Delft, Leiden, Gouda, Haarlem, Deventer and &#x2019;s Hertogenbosch which are worth a visit.</p>
      <p>There are also even smaller places with an almost complete defensive structure (walls) including the surrounding water around it. You can walk on these walls and enjoy the historical town from any viewpoint. The most impressive ones are at Willemstad, Hulst and Brielle.</p>
      <p>For a more Burgundian way of life, visit Maastricht, a city in south eastern Netherlands, near Belgium. There are many terraces where you can enjoy good food and drinks, while soaking in the historical setting of churches, squares and beautiful restored buildings.</p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <h>Kinderdijk Mills and other windmills</h>
      <p>A UNESCO World Heritage Site since 1997, the mill network at Kinderdijk-Elshout consists of 19 windmills, built in 1740. If you want to appreciate the windmills, it is best to go on foot or better; rent a bicycle and take a ride along all of the windmills. Sometimes, it is possible to visit one inside.</p>
      <p>Of course, there are more windmills than the ones in Kinderdijk. Actually, when visiting smaller towns in the Netherlands, you are likely to see lots of them and a visit to one of them often is a possibility.</p>
      <figure align="center">
        <video src="http://www.youtube.com/v/vScgEp3uIDE" border-type="soft"/>
        <legend>Windmills at Kinderdijk</legend>
      </figure>
    </section>
    <section>
      <h>Madurodam</h>
      <p>If you are only in the Netherlands for a few days and aren't sure whether to visit the countryside, other cities, islands or anything else, a visit to Madurodam will enable you to see it all in one day! Madurodam is the Netherlands on a 1:25 scale. You can enjoy most major cities and important buildings in the country by visiting this park in The Hague.</p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <h>Castles</h>
      <p>The Netherlands have a lot of beautifully located and restored castles. Many of these castles are in the central parts of the country and in the southeastern province of Limburg. One of the most beautiful castles is De Haar Castle.</p>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>
